## James Siddle

T: 07930 470122 E: jim@jamessiddle.net W: www.jamessiddle.net



#### **About Jim**

A Technical Product leader and Software Engineer with a strong track record in delivery and innovation across several major tech companies and start-ups. I help clients to apply cutting edge technology to solve challenging real-world problems, and ultimately to build and launch successful products that customers love.

I specialize in data-centric products, such as knowledge integration and discovery, data analytics and visualization, and large-scale data processing applications.

### Notable Achievements

- Established the product strategy for highly-valued start-up Stratified Medical, launched novel products for drug discovery.
- Led the product development and delivery of SureChem, a sophisticated search engine based on chemistry data mined from patents.
- Developed major enhancements to IBM's flagship messaging products.
- Two patents filed at IBM (prevention of DoS attacks, trade facilitation).
- Published articles in high-impact journals, personal blog **bibliography**

#### Education

#### **University of Oxford**

Full transcript available on request

**MSc Software Engineering — 2006-2010**, pass with distinction. Average grade A/A+, dissertation mark: 90

#### **Loughborough University**

BSc Computing — 1993-1997, first Class (honours)

#### **Guiseley School**

A-levels in Computing, Business Studies, English

## Certifications Awards

- 2016 Certified Scrum Product Owner (CSPO)
- 2013 Coursera Certifications Calculus, Machine Learning
- 2004 Chartered member of British Computer Society (MBCS CITP)
- 2003 Winner of Siemens Communications UK "Engineering Innovation Award"

#### Skills

- Leadership from small teams, to technical architecture, to product strategy, I prefer to lead by example and by setting motivating goals
- **Data-centric applications** including data mining, large-scale data processing, knowledge discovery and search, analytics and visualization.
- Programming Languages and Technologies deep technical skills in Java stack, databases, web-based technologies and numerous others from 15+ years building software products.
- Software Process primarily Scrum and Agile, TDD, BDD.
- **Architecture** design patterns, architectural patterns, modelling, UML.

## Recent Experience

References available via LinkedIn, or on request

#### Senior IT Consultant, Skyhook Consulting

London, UK — 2014-Present

Director of a small IT Consultancy company providing Product Management and Technical leadership services to software companies in London. My clients include **Stratified Medical**, **Pusher**, **European Bioinformatics Institute**, **GenenTech**.

#### Accomplishments

- Established Product Strategy for Stratified Medical, and launched innovative internal tools for novel drug discovery.
- Delivery of enriched patent dataset and data delivery mechanism for European Bioinformatics Institute.
- Product Owner for Pusher's new messaging middleware platform.

#### **Technical Product Manager, GRID / Macmillan Publishing**

London, UK — 2013-2014

Responsible for the development of new products in the Digital Science Metrics business, focused on decision support for research organizations. My primary responsibility was for a new linked-data product to support the connection and enrichment of interesting datasets across science publishing workflows.

#### Accomplishments

- Delivery of incremental versions of new linked-data product and matching services, from prototypes through to first full internal release.
- Secured adoption of the product across Digital Science businesses in line with strategic vision for an integrated product line.

## Senior Software Engineer, SureChem / Macmillan Publishing

London, UK — 2010-2013

Responsible for the architecture and development of SureChem, a sophisticated text mining product. I developed a cloud-based text processing pipeline, data storage and management systems, as well as web services and web portals.

I also worked closely with product management to elaborate requirements, helped create product roadmaps for customer presentations, supported short and long term planning, and coordinated with infrastructure teams to ensure SureChem quality of service commitments were met.

#### Accomplishments

- Designed and developed large-scale patent data processing pipeline and API for accessing core product services and data.
- Developed framework and tools for analysing quality impact of modifications in text processing technologies.
- Supported launch of SureChemDirect product, and sales activities that resulted in an anchoring sale to a major pharmaceutical company.

### Recent Experience (cont)

#### Senior Software Engineer, IBM

Winchester, UK — 2006-2010

Responsible for design, development, and delivery of numerous features and enhancements to IBM's flagship application server products, including WebSphere Application Server and Business Events products.

At IBM, I led small teams of software engineers in analysis, design, prototyping, Java-based implementation, and testing activities to meet business needs. I also took on ScrumMaster responsibilities, coached teams in Agile best practice, supported testing and documentation teams, and fixed bugs to meet product maintenance needs.

#### Accomplishments

- Design and development of multi-threaded RESTful programming interface for designing event processing applications.
- Developed integration between WebSphere Business Events and other related IBM products, to enable cross-product event handling.
- Updated WebSphere Application Server to support a new implementation of the WS-Notification standard using new Java language capabilities.
- Designed and implemented performance enhancements in the Java Messaging Service (JMS) implementation within WebSphere.

# Other Companies

#### **Software Engineer, Siemens Communications**

Nottingham, UK — 2000-2006

#### Junior Programmer, Mercia Software

Birmingham, UK — 1998-2000

#### **BSc Industrial Trainee, IBM**

Winchester, UK — 1995-1996

#### Interests

- Blogging about all things data on <u>The Variable Tree</u>
- Rock climbing in the forests of Fontainebleau in my campervan
- Travel, especially backpacking in remote areas of the world
- Games of all kinds, especially german-style board games